<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<glossary xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>Glossary</title>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>A</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="acl">
      <glossterm>ACL</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Access control list. An extended attribute associated with a file
        that contains enhanced authorization directives.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="ostfail">
      <glossterm>Administrative OST failure</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A manual configuration change to mark an OST as unavailable, so
        that operations intended for that OST fail immediately with an I/O
        error instead of waiting indefinitely for OST recovery to
        complete</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>C</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="completioncallback">
      <glossterm>Completion callback</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An RPC made by the lock server on an OST or MDT to another
        system, usually a client, to indicate that the lock is now
        granted.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="changelog">
      <glossterm>configlog</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An llog file used in a node, or retrieved from a management
        server over the network with configuration instructions for the Lustre
        file system at startup time.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="configlock">
      <glossterm>Configuration lock</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A lock held by every node in the cluster to control configuration
        changes. When the configuration is changed on the MGS, it revokes this
        lock from all nodes. When the nodes receive the blocking callback, they
        quiesce their traffic, cancel and re-enqueue the lock and wait until it
        is granted again. They can then fetch the configuration updates and
        resume normal operation.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>D</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="defaultstripepattern">
      <glossterm>Default stripe pattern</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Information in the LOV descriptor that describes the default
        stripe count, stripe size, and layout pattern used for new files in a
        file system. This can be amended by using a directory stripe descriptor
        or a per-file stripe descriptor.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="directio">
      <glossterm>Direct I/O</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A mechanism that can be used during read and write system calls
        to avoid memory cache overhead for large I/O requests. It bypasses the
        data copy between application and kernel memory, and avoids buffering
        the data in the client memory.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="dirstripdesc">
      <glossterm>Directory stripe descriptor</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An extended attribute that describes the default stripe pattern
        for new files created within that directory. This is also inherited by
        new subdirectories at the time they are created.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="DNE">
      <glossterm>Distributed Namespace Environment (DNE)</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A collection of metadata targets serving a single file
          system namespace. Without DNE, Lustre file systems are limited to a
          single metadata target for the entire name space. Without the ability 
          to distribute metadata load over multiple targets, Lustre file system
          performance may be limited. The DNE functionality has two types of
          scalability.  <emphasis>Remote Directories</emphasis> (DNE1) allows
	  sub-directories to be serviced by an independent MDT(s), increasing
	  aggregate metadata capacity and performance for independent sub-trees
	  of the filesystem. This also allows performance isolation of workloads
	  running in a specific sub-directory on one MDT from workloads on other
	  MDTs. In Lustre 2.8 and later <emphasis>Striped Directories</emphasis>
	  (DNE2) allows a single directory to be serviced by multiple MDTs.
        </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>E</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="ea">
      <glossterm>EA</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Extended attribute. A small amount of data that can be retrieved
        through a name (EA or xattr) associated with a particular inode. A
        Lustre file system uses EAs to store striping information (indicating
        the location of file data on OSTs). Examples of extended attributes are
        ACLs, striping information, and the FID of the file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="eviction">
      <glossterm>Eviction</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The process of removing a client's state from the server if the
        client is unresponsive to server requests after a timeout or if server
        recovery fails. If a client is still running, it is required to flush
        the cache associated with the server when it becomes aware that it has
        been evicted.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="export">
      <glossterm>Export</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The state held by a server for a client that is sufficient to
        transparently recover all in-flight operations when a single failure
        occurs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Extent</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A range of contiguous bytes or blocks in a file that are
        addressed by a {start, length} tuple instead of individual block
        numbers.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="extendloc">
      <glossterm>Extent lock</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An LDLM lock used by the OSC to protect an extent in a storage
        object for concurrent control of read/write, file size acquisition, and
        truncation operations.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>F</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="failback">
      <glossterm>Failback</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The failover process in which the default active server regains
        control from the backup server that had taken control of the
        service.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="failoutost">
      <glossterm>Failout OST</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An OST that is not expected to recover if it fails to answer
        client requests. A failout OST can be administratively failed, thereby
        enabling clients to return errors when accessing data on the failed OST
        without making additional network requests or waiting for OST recovery
        to complete.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="failover">
      <glossterm>Failover</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The process by which a standby computer server system takes over
        for an active computer server after a failure of the active node.
        Typically, the standby computer server gains exclusive access to a
        shared storage device between the two servers.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="fid">
      <glossterm>FID</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Lustre File Identifier. A 128-bit file system-unique identifier
        for a file or object in the file system. The FID structure contains a
        unique 64-bit sequence number (see 
        <emphasis role="italic">FLDB</emphasis>), a 32-bit object ID (OID), and
        a 32-bit version number. The sequence number is unique across all
        Lustre targets (OSTs and MDTs).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="fileset">
      <glossterm>Fileset</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A group of files that are defined through a directory that
        represents the start point of a file system.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="fldb">
      <glossterm>FLDB</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>FID location database. This database maps a sequence of FIDs to a
        specific target (MDT or OST), which manages the objects within the
        sequence. The FLDB is cached by all clients and servers in the file
        system, but is typically only modified when new servers are added to
        the file system.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="flightgroup">
      <glossterm>Flight group</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Group of I/O RPCs initiated by the OSC that are concurrently
        queued or processed at the OST. Increasing the number of RPCs in flight
        for high latency networks can increase throughput and reduce visible
        latency at the client.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>G</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="glimpsecallback">
      <glossterm>Glimpse callback</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An RPC made by an OST or MDT to another system (usually a client)
        to indicate that a held extent lock should be surrendered. If the
        system is using the lock, then the system should return the object size
        and timestamps in the reply to the glimpse callback instead of
        cancelling the lock. Glimpses are introduced to optimize the
        acquisition of file attributes without introducing contention on an
        active lock.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>I</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="import">
      <glossterm>Import</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The state held held by the client for each target that it is
        connected to. It holds server NIDs, connection state, and uncommitted
        RPCs needed to fully recover a transaction sequence after a server
        failure and restart.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="intentlock">
      <glossterm>Intent lock</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A special Lustre file system locking operation in the Linux
        kernel. An intent lock combines a request for a lock with the full
        information to perform the operation(s) for which the lock was
        requested. This offers the server the option of granting the lock or
        performing the operation and informing the client of the operation
        result without granting a lock. The use of intent locks enables
        metadata operations (even complicated ones) to be implemented with a
        single RPC from the client to the server.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>L</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="lbug">
      <glossterm>LBUG</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A fatal error condition detected by the software that halts
        execution of the kernel thread to avoid potential further corruption of
        the system state. It is printed to the console log and triggers a dump
        of the internal debug log. The system must be rebooted to clear this
        state.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="ldlm">
      <glossterm>LDLM</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Lustre Distributed Lock Manager.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lfs">
      <glossterm>lfs</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The Lustre file system command-line utility that allows end users
        to interact with Lustre software features, such as setting or checking
        file striping or per-target free space. For more details, see 
        <xref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         linkend="userutilities.lfs" />.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lfsck">
      <glossterm>LFSCK</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Lustre file system check. A distributed version of a disk file
        system checker. Normally, 
        <literal>lfsck</literal> does not need to be run, except when file
        systems are damaged by events such as multiple disk failures and cannot
        be recovered using file system journal recovery.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="llite">
      <glossterm>llite</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Lustre lite. This term is in use inside code and in module names
        for code that is related to the Linux client VFS interface.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="llog">
      <glossterm>llog</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Lustre log. An efficient log data structure used internally by
        the file system for storing configuration and distributed transaction
        records. An 
        <literal>llog</literal> is suitable for rapid transactional appends of
        records and cheap cancellation of records through a bitmap.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="llogcatalog">
      <glossterm>llog catalog</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Lustre log catalog. An 
        <literal>llog</literal> with records that each point at an 
        <literal>llog</literal>. Catalogs were introduced to give 
        <literal>llogs</literal> increased scalability. 
        <literal>llogs</literal> have an originator which writes records and a
        replicator which cancels records when the records are no longer
        needed.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lmv">
      <glossterm>LMV</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Logical metadata volume. A module that implements a DNE
        client-side abstraction device. It allows a client to work with many
        MDTs without changes to the llite module. The LMV code forwards
        requests to the correct MDT based on name or directory striping
        information and merges replies into a single result to pass back to the
        higher 
        <literal>llite</literal> layer that connects the Lustre file system with
        Linux VFS, supports VFS semantics, and complies with POSIX interface
        specifications.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lnd">
      <glossterm>LND</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Lustre network driver. A code module that enables LNet support
        over particular transports, such as TCP and various kinds of InfiniBand
        networks.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lnet">
      <glossterm>LNet</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Lustre networking. A message passing network protocol capable of
        running and routing through various physical layers. LNet forms the
        underpinning of LNETrpc.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lockclient">
      <glossterm>Lock client</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A module that makes lock RPCs to a lock server and handles
        revocations from the server.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lockserver">
      <glossterm>Lock server</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A service that is co-located with a storage target that manages
        locks on certain objects. It also issues lock callback requests, calls
        while servicing or, for objects that are already locked, completes lock
        requests.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lov">
      <glossterm>LOV</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Logical object volume. The object storage analog of a logical
        volume in a block device volume management system, such as LVM or EVMS.
        The LOV is primarily used to present a collection of OSTs as a single
        device to the MDT and client file system drivers.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lovdes">
      <glossterm>LOV descriptor</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A set of configuration directives which describes which nodes are
        OSS systems in the Lustre cluster and providing names for their
        OSTs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lustreclient">
      <glossterm>Lustre client</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An operating instance with a mounted Lustre file system.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="lustrefile">
      <glossterm>Lustre file</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A file in the Lustre file system. The implementation of a Lustre
        file is through an inode on a metadata server that contains references
        to a storage object on OSSs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>M</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="mballoc">
      <glossterm>mballoc</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Multi-block allocate. Functionality in ext4 that enables the 
        <literal>ldiskfs</literal> file system to allocate multiple blocks with
        a single request to the block allocator.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="mdc">
      <glossterm>MDC</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Metadata client. A Lustre client component that sends metadata
        requests via RPC over LNet to the metadata target (MDT).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="mdd">
      <glossterm>MDD</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Metadata disk device. Lustre server component that interfaces
        with the underlying object storage device to manage the Lustre file
        system namespace (directories, file ownership, attributes).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="mds">
      <glossterm>MDS</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Metadata server. The server node that is hosting the metadata
        target (MDT).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="mdt">
      <glossterm>MDT</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Metadata target. A storage device containing the file system
        namespace that is made available over the network to a client. It
        stores filenames, attributes, and the layout of OST objects that store
        the file data.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="mdt0">
      <glossterm>MDT0000</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The metadata target storing the file system root directory, as
          well as some core services such as quota tables.  Multiple metadata
          targets are possible in the same file system. MDT0000 must be
          available for the file system to be accessible.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="mgs">
      <glossterm>MGS</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Management service. A software module that manages the startup
        configuration and changes to the configuration. Also, the server node
        on which this system runs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="mountconf">
      <glossterm>mountconf</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The Lustre configuration protocol that formats disk file systems
        on servers with the 
        <literal>mkfs.lustre</literal> program, and prepares them for automatic
        incorporation into a Lustre cluster. This allows clients to be
        configured and mounted with a simple 
        <literal>mount</literal> command.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>N</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="nid">
      <glossterm>NID</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Network identifier. Encodes the type, network number, and network
        address of a network interface on a node for use by the Lustre file
        system.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="nioapi">
      <glossterm>NIO API</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A subset of the LNet RPC module that implements a library for
        sending large network requests, moving buffers with RDMA.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="nodeaffdef">
      <glossterm>Node affinity</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Node affinity describes the property of a multi-threaded
        application to behave sensibly on multiple cores. Without the property
        of node affinity, an operating scheduler may move application threads
        across processors in a sub-optimal way that significantly reduces
        performance of the application overall.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="nrs">
      <glossterm>NRS</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Network request scheduler. A subcomponent of the PTLRPC layer,
        which specifies the order in which RPCs are handled at servers. This
        allows optimizing large numbers of incoming requests for disk access
        patterns, fairness between clients, and other administrator-selected
        policies.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="NUMAdef">
      <glossterm>NUMA</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Non-uniform memory access. Describes a multi-processing
        architecture where the time taken to access given memory differs
        depending on memory location relative to a given processor. Typically
        machines with multiple sockets are NUMA architectures.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>O</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="odb">
      <glossterm>OBD</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Object-based device. The generic term for components in the
        Lustre software stack that can be configured on the client or server.
        Examples include MDC, OSC, LOV, MDT, and OST.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="odbtype">
      <glossterm>OBD type</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Module that can implement the Lustre object or metadata APIs.
        Examples of OBD types include the LOV, OSC and OSD.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="objectstorage">
      <glossterm>Object storage</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Refers to a storage-device API or protocol involving storage
        objects. The two most well known instances of object storage are the
        T10 iSCSI storage object protocol and the Lustre object storage
        protocol (a network implementation of the Lustre object API). The
        principal difference between the Lustre protocol and T10 protocol is
        that the Lustre protocol includes locking and recovery control in the
        protocol and is not tied to a SCSI transport layer.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="opencache">
      <glossterm>opencache</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A cache of open file handles. This is a performance enhancement
        for NFS.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="orphanobjects">
      <glossterm>Orphan objects</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Storage objects to which no Lustre file points. Orphan objects
        can arise from crashes and are automatically removed by an 
        <literal>llog</literal> recovery between the MDT and OST. When a client
        deletes a file, the MDT unlinks it from the namespace. If this is the
        last link, it will atomically add the OST objects into a per-OST 
        <literal>llog</literal>(if a crash has occurred) and then wait until
        the unlink commits to disk. (At this point, it is safe to destroy the
        OST objects. Once the destroy is committed, the MDT 
        <literal>llog</literal> records can be cancelled.)</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="osc">
      <glossterm>OSC</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Object storage client. The client module communicating to an OST
        (via an OSS).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="osd">
      <glossterm>OSD</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Object storage device. A generic, industry term for storage
        devices with a more extended interface than block-oriented devices such
        as disks. For the Lustre file system, this name is used to describe a
        software module that implements an object storage API in the kernel. It
        is also used to refer to an instance of an object storage device
        created by that driver. The OSD device is layered on a file system,
        with methods that mimic create, destroy and I/O operations on file
        inodes.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="oss">
      <glossterm>OSS</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Object storage server. A server OBD that provides access to local
        OSTs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="ost">
      <glossterm>OST</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Object storage target. An OSD made accessible through a network
        protocol. Typically, an OST is associated with a unique OSD which, in
        turn is associated with a formatted disk file system on the server
        containing the data objects.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>P</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="pdirops">
      <glossterm>pdirops</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A locking protocol in the Linux VFS layer that allows for
        directory operations performed in parallel.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="pool">
      <glossterm>Pool</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>OST pools allows the administrator to associate a name with an
        arbitrary subset of OSTs in a Lustre cluster. A group of OSTs can be
        combined into a named pool with unique access permissions and stripe
        characteristics.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="portal">
      <glossterm>Portal</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A service address on an LNet NID that binds requests to a
        specific request service, such as an MDS, MGS, OSS, or LDLM. Services
        may listen on multiple portals to ensure that high priority messages
        are not queued behind many slow requests on another portal.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="ptlrpc">
      <glossterm>PTLRPC</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An RPC protocol layered on LNet. This protocol deals with
        stateful servers and has exactly-once semantics and built in support
        for recovery.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>R</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="recovery">
      <glossterm>Recovery</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The process that re-establishes the connection state when a
        client that was previously connected to a server reconnects after the
        server restarts.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="remotedirectories">
      <glossterm>Remote directory</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A remote directory describes a feature of Lustre where metadata
	for files in a given directory may be stored on a different MDT than
	the metadata for the parent directory.  This is sometimes referred
	to as DNE1.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="replay">
      <glossterm>Replay request</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The concept of re-executing a server request after the server has
        lost information in its memory caches and shut down. The replay
        requests are retained by clients until the server(s) have confirmed
        that the data is persistent on disk. Only requests for which a client
        received a reply and were assigned a transaction number by the server
        are replayed. Requests that did not get a reply are resent.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="resent">
      <glossterm>Resent request</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An RPC request sent from a client to a server that has not had a
        reply from the server. This might happen if the request was lost on the
        way to the server, if the reply was lost on the way back from the
        server, or if the server crashes before or after processing the
        request. During server RPC recovery processing, resent requests are
        processed after replayed requests, and use the client RPC XID to
        determine if the resent RPC request was already executed on the
        server.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="revocation">
      <glossterm>Revocation callback</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Also called a "blocking callback". An RPC request made by the
        lock server (typically for an OST or MDT) to a lock client to revoke a
        granted DLM lock.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="rootsquash">
      <glossterm>Root squash</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A mechanism whereby the identity of a root user on a client
        system is mapped to a different identity on the server to avoid root
        users on clients from accessing or modifying root-owned files on the
        servers. This does not prevent root users on the client from assuming
        the identity of a non-root user, so should not be considered a robust
        security mechanism. Typically, for management purposes, at least one
        client system should not be subject to root squash.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="routing">
      <glossterm>Routing</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>LNet routing between different networks and LNDs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="rpc">
      <glossterm>RPC</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Remote procedure call. A network encoding of a request.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>S</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="stripe">
      <glossterm>Stripe</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A contiguous, logical extent of a Lustre file written to a single
        OST. Used synonymously with a single OST data object that makes up part
        of a file visible to user applications.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="stripeddirectory" condition='l28'>
      <glossterm>Striped Directory</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A striped directory is when metadata for files in a given
	directory are distributed evenly over multiple MDTs. Striped directories
        are only available in Lustre software version 2.8 or later.
        A user can create a striped directory to increase metadata
	performance of large directories by distributing the metadata
	requests in a single directory over two or more MDTs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="stridesize">
      <glossterm>Stripe size</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The maximum number of bytes that will be written to an OST object
        before the next object in a file's layout is used when writing
        sequential data to a file. Once a full stripe has been written to each
        of the objects in the layout, the first object will be written to again
        in round-robin fashion.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="stripcount">
      <glossterm>Stripe count</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The number of OSTs holding objects for a RAID0-striped Lustre
        file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>T</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="t10">
      <glossterm>T10 object protocol</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>An object storage protocol tied to the SCSI transport layer. The
        Lustre file system does not use T10.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>W</title>
    <glossentry xml:id="widestriping">
      <glossterm>Wide striping</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Strategy of using many OSTs to store stripes of a single file.
        This obtains maximum bandwidth access to a single file through parallel
        utilization of many OSTs. For more information about wide striping, see
        
        <xref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
        linkend="wide_striping" />.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
</glossary>
<!--
  vim:expandtab:shiftwidth=2:tabstop=8:
  -->
