<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legalnotice xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en-US">
    <title>Important Notice from Intel</title>

    <para>INFORMATION IN THIS DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED IN CONNECTION WITH INTEL PRODUCTS.  NO LICENSE, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, BY ESTOPPEL OR OTHERWISE, TO ANY INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS IS GRANTED BY THIS DOCUMENT.  EXCEPT AS PROVIDED IN INTEL'S TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF SALE FOR SUCH PRODUCTS, INTEL ASSUMES NO LIABILITY WHATSOEVER AND INTEL DISCLAIMS ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTY, RELATING TO SALE AND/OR USE OF INTEL PRODUCTS INCLUDING LIABILITY OR WARRANTIES RELATING TO FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR INFRINGEMENT OF ANY PATENT, COPYRIGHT OR OTHER INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHT.</para>

    <para>A "Mission Critical Application" is any application in which failure of the Intel Product could result, directly or indirectly, in personal injury or death.  SHOULD YOU PURCHASE OR USE INTEL'S PRODUCTS FOR ANY SUCH MISSION CRITICAL APPLICATION, YOU SHALL INDEMNIFY AND HOLD INTEL AND ITS SUBSIDIARIES, SUBCONTRACTORS AND AFFILIATES, AND THE DIRECTORS, OFFICERS, AND EMPLOYEES OF EACH, HARMLESS AGAINST ALL CLAIMS COSTS, DAMAGES, AND EXPENSES AND REASONABLE ATTORNEYS' FEES ARISING OUT OF, DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY, ANY CLAIM OF PRODUCT LIABILITY, PERSONAL INJURY, OR DEATH ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF SUCH MISSION CRITICAL APPLICATION, WHETHER OR NOT INTEL OR ITS SUBCONTRACTOR WAS NEGLIGENT IN THE DESIGN, MANUFACTURE, OR WARNING OF THE INTEL PRODUCT OR ANY OF ITS PARTS.</para>

    <para>Intel may make changes to specifications and product descriptions at any time, without notice.  Designers must not rely on the absence or characteristics of any features or instructions marked "reserved" or "undefined".  Intel reserves these for future definition and shall have no responsibility whatsoever for conflicts or incompatibilities arising from future changes to them.  The information here is subject to change without notice.  Do not finalize a design with this information.</para>

    <para>The products described in this document may contain design defects or errors known as errata which may cause the product to deviate from published specifications.  Current characterized errata are available on request.</para>

    <para>Contact your local Intel sales office or your distributor to obtain the latest specifications and before placing your product order.</para>

    <para>Copies of documents which have an order number and are referenced in this document, or other Intel literature, may be obtained by calling 1-800-548-4725, or go to: http://www.intel.com/design/literature.htm</para>

    <para>Intel and the Intel logo are trademarks of Intel Corporation in the U.S. and/or other countries. Lustre is a registered trademark of Oracle Corporation.</para>

    <para><superscript>*</superscript>Other names and brands may be claimed as the property of
        others.</para>

    <para>THE ORIGINAL LUSTRE 2.x FILESYSTEM: OPERATIONS MANUAL HAS BEEN MODIFIED: THIS OPERATIONS MANUAL IS A MODIFIED VERSION OF, AND IS DERIVED FROM, THE LUSTRE 2.0 FILESYSTEM: OPERATIONS MANUAL PUBLISHED BY ORACLE AND AVAILABLE AT [http://www.lustre.org/].  MODIFICATIONS (collectively, the “Modifications”) HAVE BEEN MADE BY INTEL CORPORATION (“Intel”).  ORACLE AND ITS AFFILIATES HAVE NOT REVIEWED, APPROVED, SPONSORED, OR ENDORSED THIS MODIFIED OPERATIONS MANUAL, OR ENDORSED INTEL, AND ORACLE AND ITS AFFILIATES ARE NOT RESPONSIBLE OR LIABLE FOR ANY MODIFICATIONS THAT INTEL HAS MADE TO THE ORIGINAL OPERATIONS MANUAL.</para>

    <para>NOTHING IN THIS MODIFIED OPERATIONS MANUAL IS INTENDED TO AFFECT THE NOTICE PROVIDED BY ORACLE BELOW IN RESPECT OF THE ORIGINAL OPERATIONS MANUAL AND SUCH ORACLE NOTICE CONTINUES TO APPLY TO THIS MODIFIED OPERATIONS MANUAL EXCEPT FOR THE MODIFICATIONS; THIS INTEL NOTICE SHALL APPLY ONLY TO MODIFICATIONS MADE BY INTEL.  AS BETWEEN YOU AND ORACLE: (I) NOTHING IN THIS INTEL NOTICE IS INTENDED TO AFFECT THE TERMS OF THE ORACLE NOTICE BELOW; AND (II) IN THE EVENT OF ANY CONFLICT BETWEEN THE TERMS OF THIS INTEL NOTICE AND THE TERMS OF THE ORACLE NOTICE, THE ORACLE NOTICE SHALL PREVAIL.
    </para>

    <para>Your use of any Intel software shall be governed by separate license terms containing restrictions on use and disclosure and are protected by intellectual property laws.</para>

    <para>The information contained herein is subject to change without notice and is not warranted to be error-free.  If you find any errors, please report them to us in writing.</para>

    <para>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 United States License. To view a copy of this license and obtain more information about Creative Commons licensing, visit Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 United States [http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/us] or send a letter to Creative Commons, 171 2nd Street, Suite 300, San Francisco, California 94105, USA.</para>

</legalnotice>
<!--vim:expandtab:shiftwidth=2:tabstop=8:-->
