<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en-US"
 xml:id="managingfailover">
  <title xml:id="managingfailover.title">Lustre File System Failover and Multiple-Mount Protection</title>
  <para>This chapter describes the multiple-mount protection (MMP) feature, which protects the file
    system from being mounted simultaneously to more than one node. It includes the following
    sections:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><xref linkend="dbdoclet.50438213_13563"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><xref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="section_etn_4zf_tl"/></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <note>
    <para>For information about configuring a Lustre file system for failover, see <xref
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="configuringfailover"/></para>
  </note>
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50438213_13563">
      <title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>multiple-mount protection</primary>
      </indexterm> Overview of Multiple-Mount Protection</title>
    <para>The multiple-mount protection (MMP) feature protects the Lustre file system from being
      mounted simultaneously to more than one node. This feature is important in a shared storage
      environment (for example, when a failover pair of OSSs share a LUN).</para>
    <para>The backend file system, <literal>ldiskfs</literal>, supports the MMP mechanism. A block
      in the file system is updated by a <literal>kmmpd</literal> daemon at one second intervals,
      and a sequence number is written in this block. If the file system is cleanly unmounted, then
      a special &quot;clean&quot; sequence is written to this block. When mounting the file system,
        <literal>ldiskfs</literal> checks if the MMP block has a clean sequence or not.</para>
    <para>Even if the MMP block has a clean sequence, <literal>ldiskfs</literal> waits for some interval to guard against the following situations:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> If I/O traffic is heavy, it may take longer for the MMP block to be updated.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> If another node is trying to mount the same file system, a &quot;race&quot; condition may occur.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>With MMP enabled, mounting a clean file system takes at least 10 seconds. If the file system was not cleanly unmounted, then the file system mount may require additional time.</para>
    <note>
      <para>The MMP feature is only supported on Linux kernel versions newer than 2.6.9.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section_etn_4zf_tl">
    <title>Working with Multiple-Mount Protection</title>
    <para>On a new Lustre file system, MMP is automatically enabled by
        <literal>mkfs.lustre</literal> at format time if failover is being used and the kernel and
        <literal>e2fsprogs</literal> version support it. On an existing file system, a Lustre file
      system administrator can manually enable MMP when the file system is unmounted.</para>
    <para>Use the following commands to determine whether MMP is running in the Lustre file system
      and to enable or disable the MMP feature.</para>
    <para>To determine if MMP is enabled, run:</para>
    <screen>dumpe2fs -h <replaceable>/dev/block_device</replaceable> | grep mmp</screen>
    <para>Here is a sample command:</para>
    <screen>dumpe2fs -h /dev/sdc | grep mmp 
Filesystem features: has_journal ext_attr resize_inode dir_index 
filetype extent mmp sparse_super large_file uninit_bg</screen>
    <para>To manually disable MMP, run:</para>
    <screen>tune2fs -O ^mmp <replaceable>/dev/block_device</replaceable></screen>
    <para>To manually enable MMP, run:</para>
    <screen>tune2fs -O mmp <replaceable>/dev/block_device</replaceable></screen>
    <para>When MMP is enabled, if <literal>ldiskfs</literal> detects multiple mount attempts after
      the file system is mounted, it blocks these later mount attempts and reports the time when the
      MMP block was last updated, the node name, and the device name of the node where the file
      system is currently mounted.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!--vim:expandtab:shiftwidth=2:tabstop=8:-->
